<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Tycho Protocol Updates</title>
    <description>Research updates and progress on scaling trust in research data</description>
    <link>https://tblomseth.github.io/tychodocs/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@tycho-protocol.org (Tycho Protocol Team)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@tycho-protocol.org (Tycho Protocol Team)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 06:44:17 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 06:44:17 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Tycho Protocol Build System</generator>

    <item>
      <title>Authentic Sound - Why Audio Provenance Needs Hardware-Level Trust</title>
      <description><![CDATA[**Background - Domain-Specific Clients** The disturbance we're experiencing as AI tools infiltrate every dimension of work is so deep and so general that it's become hard, logically and psychologically, to pause long enough within the borders any particular domain and consider its specific requirements. Every concrete example immediately suggests a hundred analogs, and it seems almost foolish to pay close attention to, say, the complaints of teachers about AI assisted cheating, the worries of visual artists about robot competition, the contamination of research data by simulated observational records, and the disappearance of entry-level jobs. Aren't these all versions of the same problem? The answer is no. Although we have been developing a low-level, domain-agnostic approach to securing digital data provenance, its real-world usefulness depends entirely on the technical stack; and, as anyone who has worked with enterprise software knows, the specificity and heterogeneity of these stacks across various domains is almost impossible to overstate. Even where a Borg-like vendor—Salesforce, Microsoft, Google—offers a supposedly universal platform, actual deployments rely on endless customizations, extensions, and workarounds that defeat true uniformity. So, although we envision securing trust in data across domains, we've had to come to terms with fact that Tycho clients will have endless variety. We've committed ourselves to creating some reference implementations in key domains, but we predict that these implementations will never be real products. Instead, they can be understood as documents, showing what Tycho can do and teaching developers (human and robot) how to think about the Tycho network. This first post on domain-specific clients will focus on audio engineering, asking the question: How can we render audio files more trustworthy? **Audio Forensics** Voice cloning has gone from a laboratory novelty to a cheap commodity within the last twenty-four months. This shift has operationalized what researchers call the Liar's Dividend: the ability for public figures to dismiss authentic, damaging recordings as "AI-generated," thereby eroding the objective value of audio provenance. **The Damage Is Already Done** *Political Decoy and Suppression*: In Slovakia's 2023 election, a deepfake audio clip of pro-EU candidate Michal Šimečka discussing election rigging surfaced 48 hours before polls opened—during a mandatory media silence period when he could not legally rebut it. Analysts believe it contributed to his pro-Russian opponent's victory. In 2024, thousands of New Hampshire voters received an AI-cloned call from "President Biden" telling them to skip the primary, leading to the first FCC ruling outlawing AI-generated voices in robocalls. *Corporate and Financial Fraud*: A Hong Kong multinational lost $25 million in 2024 after an employee joined a video call with deepfaked executives. The audio authenticity was the psychological anchor that convinced him to wire the funds. *Personal Security*: Arizona mother Jennifer DeStefano received a call from what sounded exactly like her 15-year-old daughter crying and pleading for help, followed by a ransom demand. This "virtual kidnapping" tactic now uses as little as 3 seconds of social media audio to clone a relative's voice. *Legal Precedents*: Tennessee's 2024 ELVIS Act became the first US law to protect a person's voice as a property right, moving audio provenance into intellectual property litigation. **Why Watermarking Falls Short** Simple watermarking cannot solve this problem. It doesn't protect against upstream fakery—a synthetic recording can be watermarked too. It isn't anchored into real-world time, so backdating is trivial. And it doesn't guarantee the instrument: there's no proof the audio came from a specific, verified microphone rather than a text-to-speech engine. **Where in the Stack? Why It Matters** Each layer in the audio stack—from applications down through sound servers, libraries, kernel APIs, drivers, to the hardware ADC—represents an opportunity for manipulation. An application-level signature leaves every layer below it unattested. A bad actor could inject synthetic audio anywhere in the chain, then sign the result with perfect legitimacy. The signature proves only that *someone* signed *something*; it says nothing about what actually happened at the microphone. The closer we move Tycho toward the digital-physical border, the smaller the attack surface. At the driver level, we can hash and sign audio buffers the moment they arrive from the ADC, before any userspace process can touch them. This is what makes hardware-level attestation fundamentally different from file-level signing: the guarantees propagate downstream to every application that consumes the audio. **The Tycho Questions: What True Provenance Answers** The Tycho protocol provides cryptographic answers to five essential questions about any recording: *Temporal Anchoring* (when exactly was this captured?), *Instrument Authenticity* (which specific device made this recording?), *Sequentiality* (is the order of audio samples mathematically guaranteed?), *Immutability* (has any alteration occurred since capture?), and *Custody* (who has handled this data?). **The Linux Audio Community Shows the Way** The open-source Linux audio community—maintainers of ALSA kernel drivers, the Bela platform, and dozens of open hardware projects—can integrate Tycho at the digital-physical border where analog becomes digital. By hashing and signing audio the moment it leaves the ADC, before any software can touch it, open audio can establish a new standard: recordings that are authentic by design, not by assertion. Authentic sound is possible. *Thank you to the extraordinary audio tools maker Billy Putnam for the fascinating discussion that guided us to the open source audio community.*]]></description>
      <pubDate>29 Dec 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://tycho.article-27.org/#updates</link>
      <guid>tycho-Authentic -0</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protocol Testing Phase</title>
      <description><![CDATA[Test update 3]]></description>
      <pubDate>23 Sep 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://tycho.article-27.org/#updates</link>
      <guid>tycho-Protocol T-0</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Website Launch</title>
      <description><![CDATA[Test update 2]]></description>
      <pubDate>15 Sep 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://tycho.article-27.org/#updates</link>
      <guid>tycho-Website La-0</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initial Framework</title>
      <description><![CDATA[Test update 1]]></description>
      <pubDate>01 Sep 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://tycho.article-27.org/#updates</link>
      <guid>tycho-Initial Fr-0</guid>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
